this is a
question on
Delight how is it that Delight in
agreeable sense experiences that are
provocative of lust lead to suffering
when it clearly gets you immediate
pleasure you know I said it's
provocative lust this leads to suffering
this kind of delighting in sense
Pleasures that yes understand
but you get immediate pleasure you get
IM me the pleasure and does this mean
that if an agreeable thing is not
provocative of lust then it is okay to
Delight in
it so um giving the immediate
pleasure well we don't have to really
look anywhere further than the often
used similo scratch in the
itch you have a skin
infection it hurts it's not getting
better scratching immediately relieves
it immediately but relieves it only
because your starting point is
pain so nobody denies that delight and
sensuality offers a form of
satisfaction but you need to look at the
bigger picture and recognize that hold
on but it's only satisfaction from what
was imposed on me the pain the pressure
the necessity to
act so that's not not really a
satisfaction I should be cultivating
because that satisfaction is increasing
that dependence so the more you scratch
the more will itch the more you will
need to
scratch so the true satisfaction then is
to to heal your skin condition whereby
there is no itch to begin with and
that's much more peaceful and better
even for the one that still enjoys
scratching it yeah it would be better if
I'm not sick to begin with if I'm not
addicted to begin with so like
some medicines are like those counter
irritant the cream so you got a pain in
your elbow whatever you put a cream on
it which it's like Menthol Burns counter
irritates that m m that pain I don't but
it doesn't make the pain worse whereas
this uh this but yeah increases the
infection yeah exactly exactly increases
your dependence on that
so what was the other question should
you then if it's not provocative of lust
should you be delighting yeah well you
wouldn't be delighting
it yes good so if there is no lust there
will be no Delight there might be still
pleasure so the question should be
reformulated whereby if the pleasure is
not provocative of lust or Delight can I
be fine with it or do I have to also
like um be vigilant and well you have to
be vigilant one way or the other but uh
the point is it's the Delight is bound
with sensuality you're delighting at the
prospect of relief so usually one one
wants to know how how do you know the
difference how can you really know is
this pleasure that I'm experiencing this
sense object that I'm experiencing that
is
pleasurable is it okay to
experience it too so you can know the
it too so you can know the
difference by recognizing as I said that
you don't start from a neutral
position it's not like you're not
affected by craving for more pleasure as
means of escaping
pain and it's not like you your position
is this clear perspective from which you
can clearly see uh pleasure of
sensuality and pleasure of
non-sensuality so in the beginning
pretty much everything will be infected
with your craving and your Delight and
need to scratch so the way to see the
difference is to restrain that first to
not act out of it then within that you
get to recognize the nuances of oh hold
on but actually this pleasure is not uh
does not lead to to increasing of The
Thirst increasing of possession and and
and and gaining and activity and stuff
is just for for what it is so then um
and that's exactly what the Buddha was
saying in the sutas as well like in the
beginning he himself had to renounce the
pleasures had to like
say no you know this leads to suffering
but then within that he hold on actually
why am I fearing these other Pleasures
pleasures of renunciation why don't need
to fear
that but initially he he wasn't sure
whether he should fear that as
well because you your position is not
neutral in the beginning so you have to
start okay because you've been going one
way only before now you have to start
going the other way completely and then
within that you recognize okay I don't
need to go as far but if you want to
predetermine that before you start
walking that path of restraint and
renunciation to whatever degree if you
want to predetermine it and make sense
out of it and and like intellectually
clarify all the facets of it before you
do it that's
impossible logic cannot reason cannot
access that in a sense that uh reason
alone cannot access that in a sense that
you you need to actually be living it
and practicing it as a modes of choice
they would then reveal the new field for
your reason to to to develop inside into
oh yeah that's the pleasure of
anunciation that's the pleasure of
sensuality but that choice if you don't
cultivate those right choices of
renunciation those fields will not
become apparent so you'll be thinking
about your ideas that are already on the
basis of sensuality your ideas of
renunciation your ideas of the
differences that are on the basis very
much of your current Central
being so about only by practicing that
renunciation be able to tell you start
really being able to tell the difference
between what is sensual you able to see
sensual is highlighting that basically
what is what is um provocative of thirst
what is increasing it that will be
clearer clearer and clearer yeah and
that which doesn't increase your
suffering saying that's that would be
clear as well be clear eventually yeah
like reference of what increases
suffering or not will not necessarily
cannot be necessarily trusted to begin
with because abstaining from it will
increase your suffering mhh yeah so and
that's exactly why people don't do it
because well look isn't D supposed to be
free me from
suffering uh but I suffer more well yes
you need to suffer more
initially but it's more like just if you
commit to the to the renunciation and
ification of the
behavior the difference between the
pleasure that's kind of undermining you
with that pressure and thirst for more
and it's kind of basically taking its
own momentum if you give into and then
you just going to be a puppet to serve
the Fulfillment of it you can't stop
once you start you'll know oh that's
yeah that's that that should not be even
even even entertained mentally but then
you realize there is other pleasure
there's other agreeability that is that
do not possess that same
quality it's like okay I don't I'll be
careful in case it becomes that but it's
not and that's often be so I shouldn't
go for a walk or or this or that because
it's ental it's like well again is it is
it something that you won't be able to
sleep over obsessed obsessing your mind
over obsessed obsessing your mind
provocative of lust inducing The Thirst
inducing the fear anxiety if you get it
if you don't it's
not so yes there might be traces of your
craving but you have bigger fish to fry
now develop the impeccable restraint in
regard to things that are factually full
on sensuality ill will desire that
revolves around it when that would have
been purified that layer okay now deal
with these subtler ones of how you eat
why you eat and all of
that because yes you know there there
there's going to be some traces of it
but it's not you can't be as I said
before you know purifying the
gold with like a pair of finest tweezers
picking up the slightest little
impurities from the melted liquid while
the thing is still like swimming in
feces and stuff so it's like it's a
pointless task you got to remove the coar
task you got to remove the coar
impurities first and then you'll see
what what the next step is